Code indentation

The old tabs versus spaces argument

Honestly, how you choose to indent your code is up to you. Some people use tabs, some people use spaces, and either option if fine. However, it drives me bonkers when people argue that everyone needs to indent using spaces. Really? Spaces are a horrible way to indent compared to tabs.

Tabs are a single character

When arguing that people need to use spaces to indent, it's often said that a *certain number* of spaces should be used. Uniformity is important, after all. But what could be more uniform than indenting using tab characters? With spaces, not only do you need to decide to use spaces instead of tabs, you need to decide how many spaces to use. With tabs, it's easy. No one indents using multiple tab characters because a tab character already takes up as much space as you tell your editor to make it take up.

What is the tab character even for?

Spaces are word separators. They're not meant for indentation. Do you know what character *is* meant for indentation? It's the tab character! Why not use the tab character for what it's meant for instead of ignoring it altogether?

Spaces make it easier to line things up. When trying to line up variable names in code or when trying to put Unicode art in your source code comments, spaces are great. However, tab characters have a semantic meaning. When indenting code, tabs are the way to go.

Conclusions

I don't care how you want to indent your code. However, please stop lecturing me about why I need to use spaces instead of tabs. You're wrong. If I'm not in your employ and not making pull requests to your code, I'll indent however I please. And how I please is the only way that makes sense to me: using tab characters.

Copyright © 2017 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Free culture

Just as important as free software

Some people, such as the FSF, feel that cultural works and other nonfunctional works don't require the same freedoms as software. However, could that really be true?

Freedom of thought, of speech, of expression

Culture isn't created in a vacuum. Rather, culture builds off of the culture that came before. Everything is derivative; nothing is truly original. However, people think that it's somehow alright to hoard "their" ideas, not allowing anyone else to use them for other purposes. This is what copyright is all about. The media that we experience shapes our ideas though. Sometimes it shows us new ways of thinking, while other times, it sets our imaginations wild. However, when we're restricted from reusing and reshaping the works that we experience, we're essentially being censored. We're not allowed to express our ideas, ideas based on what we've see, we've heard, we've touched. Is that really fair? It certainly isn't freedom, and in my opinion, isn't acceptable.

Source code

The one difference between free software and free culture is the source code requirement. That is to say, it's arguable that providing the source material of nonsoftware isn't a hard requirement. It's *nice* if you provide the source material and it can be *useful* to have access to it, but it's not strictly necessary to provide it, unlike with software.

Fear of misrepresentation

The FSF cites fear of misrepresentation as the reason that they use proprietary licenses for their opinionative works. Is this really justified though? And more to the point, is it even really necessary? One could misrepresent someone by modifying their software and re-releasing it as well, so that's not a difference between cultural works and software. Additionally, some free software licenses forbid the misrepresentation of their original authors and forbid the passing off of your modified version as the original. Those *same requirements* can be implemented in free cultural licenses, and in some cases already are. There is absolutely *no excuse* for claiming that opinionative words should be under licenses that disallow modification out of fear of misrepresentation.

Forced speech is not free speech

The FSF also uses a particular nonfree license, the GFDL, to cram their opinions down the throats of others. They pack their propaganda into their manuals, saying that people either have to leave the propaganda intact, they have to rewrite the entire manual, or they have to work without a manual at all. Forced speech isn't free speech; it is an outright lie when the FSF calls this license a free documentation license.

Freedom is freedom

If you are a supporter of free software because of the freedom that it provides, you're outright inconsistent if you don't also support free culture. Why should you support freedom when it comes to *some* creative works (software), but not others (art)? The only way that it would make sense is if you're actually supporting free software strictly for the non-freedom-related practical benefits. For example, perhaps you support free software because of the privacy issues that surround proprietary software. However, the FSF claims not to be doing this. They claim to be fighting for freedom in software for the sake of freedom itself, yet they disregard freedom in media, even going as far as to trample on media freedom by releasing their works under nonfree licenses. It is for this reason that I urge you not to support the Free Software Foundation, neither with your words nor with your donations. Your support would be much better placed in someone that can be more consistent, and therefore, more understandable and more trustworthy. The Electronic Frontier Foundation, for example, would be a much better group to support.

Copyright © 2017 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Free software

Vital for trust, privacy, security, freedom, education, competition, and progress

Free software is absolutely vital for a number of reasons. Some people focus on only some reasons, then claim that people that focus on other reasons are missing the point. However, I think that in cases such as these, both sides are missing part of the point. We should all be insisting on free software and we don't need the same reason to do so. There are plenty of reasons to support free software and almost no reasons to oppose it.

Trust

Companies have proven time and time again that they can't be trusted. They frequently build malicious features into their works to pad their bottom lines. But what if there was a way to know that you could trust the software that you run? What if the human-readable source code was available for public audit and commentary? With free software, you have that. You don't even need to know how to read the code yourself. If there's something particularly malicious in the code and there is a large enough user base, *someone* will notice and publicize it. Simply having the source code available is of benefit to everyone, even those that can't make direct use of it.

Privacy

Often times, proprietary software vendors build spyware into their software. A great example of this is the spyware that Microsoft incorporated into Windows 10. There's no way to even turn it off and it's been proven to bypass your proxy settings. It sends your private data back to Microsoft, which is an invasion of privacy and is just plain creepy. Let's pretend for a moment that you fully trust Microsoft with your data though. What then? Because Microsoft doesn't care about you, they set up their operating system to send back some of your data using unencrypted HTTP. Not only is Microsoft able to see anything that they choose to on your computer, anyone listening in can perform a man-in-the-middle attack and see all of that information as well! With Windows 10, you get no privacy with your own machine.

With free software, this is much less of an issue. When the source code is widely available, someone will notice and point out when the software's doing something that invades the users' privacy. Furthermore, if the software is important enough, people with fork the code and remove the malicious feature. The malicious version of the software will lose popularity and will collapse.

Security

Security and privacy go hand-in-hand. If your machine is constantly sending your data back home to the developer of the software that you use, I'd argue that that's not only a breach of privacy and a breach of trust, but also a breach of security. However, let's put that aside and instead focus on the exploitation of vulnerabilities in the system, both intended and unintended.

Back doors

Sometimes, software developers into their software. In doing so, they provide themselves with access to all or part of your machine. Clearly, this is a breach of your security, but it doesn't stop there. Malicious computer crackers are often very skilled at locating and exploiting these back doors. By building these back doors into their software, developers not only allow themselves access to your machine, but also allow access to your machine by any number of unknown malicious parties. Back doors are quickly spotted by users and removed from software when the source code is available to the public.

Security bugs

Security bugs happen, both in free and nonfree software. But how easy are they to find and get fixed? When the source code is available, any user that notices the bug, has the skills, and has the time can fix it. Often times, the developers are more than willing to take bug patches from users that take the time and effort to fix these problems. Critical bug patches are often released within hours of a bug getting found simply because many users want the bug gone and peace of mind restored.

I'm not saying that critical security bugs are always found right away in free software. We all know about the Heartbleed incident, which went undiscovered for about two years. However, when critical bugs are discovered, fixes come almost right away.

Freedom

With free software, you have freedom. This should go without saying. If software doesn't quite work the way that you want it to, you may modify it. You may write your own bug fixes if others aren't writing them fast enough, you can deploy custom versions, and you may do all your computing your way. There's very little limit to what you can do with the software that you use when it's free.

Education

Why is proprietary software even *used* in the education system? Proprietary software usually doesn't allow you to see the source code and often forbids reverse engineering. In other words, proprietary software *forbids you from learning how it functions*. Is this really conductive to education? I don't thing so. It can be argued that schools teach about proprietary software because that's what people will use when they get a job, but that's a bit misleading. A big part of what software people choose to use is based on what they know. If schools taught about free software instead of proprietary software, we'd see a lot more free software in use by businesses.

Competition

One of the biggest problems with proprietary software is the monopolies and vendor lock-in that it creates. This leads to price gouging and often results in users giving in and accepting all of the user-abusing features that the software comes with, such as back doors and spyware. After all, what other choice do users have? However, with free software, it's easy to develop alternatives. Projects can be forked and user-abusing features can be removed. Custom interfaces can be provided, new features can be added, and users can switch between alternatives as they see fit. Users aren't bound to the whims of a single company.

Progress

Probably my biggest problem with proprietary software is the fact that everyone is having to reinvent the wheel. With free software, that which has already been developed can be reused, so development efforts can be put somewhere more productive. Hoarded knowledge has held us back so far. If people worked together instead of against one another, just imagine how much more technologically advanced we'd be by now.

Copyright © 2017 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Holidays

And anniversaries

Holidays

Holidays are incredibly arbitrary. To even observe them is to treat a single (or multiple in the case of some holidays) calendar day as somehow different than the days that surround it though. Is that day honestly any different? Not really. And yet this idea perpetuates that holidays are fantastic and that very specific actions should be taken on and around each holiday.

Practicality

Having nearly the entire workforce take the day off on a single day is highly inconvenient. You have the day off yourself, but there's errands that you can't even get done because most of the businesses are closed. Instead, a much better system would involve giving different people different days off so that you can use your days off to get done whatever you need or want to. If you want to stay at home, go out on a hike, or even hang out with friends and family, you can still do that. You may need to make sure that your days off overlap with theirs, but that's a small price to pay. However, if you need to run to the bank, you can do that as well.

Anniversaries

The problem with celebrating anniversaries is that you're not actually celebrating the day that an event happened; rather, you're celebrating a day that's exactly some number of years *after* the event. Celebrating the event again is one thing, but why do you need an arbitrary calendar date to to it on? This is especially true of ongoing things. For example, with marriage anniversaries, you no doubt intend to celebrate the fact that you're in a loving relationship, not the fact that you got together. There's no reason to celebrate on a very specific calendar date, as you're still in a loving marriage every other day of the year as well.

Birthdays

A birthday is just a very specific type of anniversary, so birthdays are just as meaningless as other anniversaries. When you celebrate a birthday, you're not celebrating the day that the person came into the world; you're celebrating the *anniversary* of that day! Besides, observing birthdays is incredibly morbid, when you think about it. With each birthday, that person draws another year closer to the grave. Is that *really* what you want to celebrate?

Arbitrary celebration

To be clear, I'm not against arbitrary celebration. By all means, celebration is a great way to unwind! However, arbitrary celebrations should be labeled as being such. For example, if you want to throw a party, just call it a party! If you want to hold a family gathering, just do it! Don't try to claim that you're doing it because of a particular holiday and don't go looking for some supposedly-meaningful calendar date to attach it to. Just find a date that's convenient for you and perhaps convenient for those that you wish to attend. Don't expect the whole world to celebrate with you on the same day. And most importantly, don't try to claim that arbitrary calendar dates hold any more value or meaning than others.

Copyright © 2017 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Misuse of words

Common problems in speech from native English speakers that can't figure out how to speak their own language correctly

When you misuse words, it makes you look stupid and/or uneducated. Please don't make the following common and idiotic mistakes. This page doesn't even deal with homonyms. If you can't figure out that the spelling "they're" is the one that's a contraction of the words "they are", being clearly the only one of the three words to be spelled with an apostrophe, you might be beyond help. As for other homonyms, if you're unsure, look them up.

ATM machine

An ATM is an automatic teller machine. The acronym "ATM" literally stands for "automatic teller machine". So what then, is an "ATM machine"? Clearly, it's an "automatic teller machine machine", whatever that is. Is it a machine that produces ATMs? Maybe. But the one thing that it most certainly *isn't* is one of those machines that allows you to deposit money into and withdraw money out of an account, because those are just ATMs.

Black and white

Black and white are two and only two colors. Neither of those colors are grey. If an image includes black, white, and grey, it's not a black and white image; it's a *greyscale* image.

Could care less

If you could dare less, it means that you must care. Otherwise, you'd be completely unable to care less than you do now. If you mean that you don't care at all, the correct phrasing is that you *couldn't* care less. If you *couldn't* care less, it means that you don't care at all, because if you did care even in the slightest, it would be possible to care less.

Did I scare you?

If you scare someone, you make them fear you. If you make a sudden noise near someone and they jump, but then they're not trying to get away from you once they know what's going on, you didn't scare them. You *startled* them.

Don't itch!

Please don't tell people not to itch. To itch is to experience the sensation of itchiness. People *cannot* make themselves not itch, except sometimes via *scratching*, which is the action that you're actually trying to prevent. If you don't want someone to *scratch*, then that's what you should say.

Less is more

Less is not more. The phrase "less is more" doesn't even make sense. Less may be *better*, and more may be *worse*, but less *cannot*, by definition, be more.

Literally

Literally means in a "in a literal sense". In other words, if you say that you are literally doing something, it means that you are actually doing it and that you don't mean that as a figure of speech. For example, if you say that you're literally dying of laughter, it means that your life is actually ending because of how much that you're laughing. Is that *really* the message that you're trying to get across? My mother is a schoolteacher, and often says that the students are literally bouncing off the walls. Are they actually bashing themselves against the walls and ricocheting off? No? Then they are *figuratively* bouncing off the walls.

Misuse of this word has gotten so bad that in dictionaries, "figuratively" is now listed as one of the definitions of this word. In other words, the language has become so corrupted that a word now means its own opposite. When something means its own opposite, the word loses all value because it no longer has a useful, distinguishing meaning. Please, quit misusing this word so that we can get its meaning fixed.

PIN number

A PIN is a personal identification number, so a "PIN number" would be a "personal identification number number". Is that some sort of meta-number that references your actual PIN?

Copyright © 2016-2017 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

XML

Extensible Markup Language

Cleaner than HTML

XML's greatest strength is that unlike HTML, it must be valid to be rendered. Rendering malformed files by default isn't the best idea. With XML, when you check out how your code looks, you can immediately see when your code's malformed so you can fix it. In HTML, such errors are often glossed over by the Web browser so you don't even see them. Before the WHATWG formed and got involved, there was another important reason to use XML as well: mobile clients. Fixing malformed markup in order to render it takes electrical power and processing power, both things that are in shorter supply on mobile clients. Had the Web moved forward with XHTML2 and HTML been discontinued, mobile clients wouldn't have to have been made to interpret bad markup. They could rely on markup to be clean, and if it wasn't, they could display the same error message that would be displayed on a desktop client. Thanks to the WHATWG though, HTML is continuing forward, despite its glaring flaws, and mobile clients will likely always spend their limited resources on cleaning up broken pages internally before rendering them.

Escape your code properly

Please don't be a lazy bastard. Don't use <![CDATA[ ]]> in your code. There are exactly zero cases in which this construct is needed. All that this construct does is allow you to be lazy and neglect to escape your <, >, and & characters. I'm not entirely certain, but it's possible that it also functions in some cases in which " or ' could need to be escaped. However, you should strive to write clean code. Simply escape your characters properly, and you won't have any issues. Escaping your characters properly even works within <script/> and <style/> tags; it doesn't interfere with the interpretation of JavaScript or CSS. That said, you shouldn't have JavaScript or CSS in the same file as your XHTML in most cases. In all but a few corner cases, JavaScript and CSS should be stored in external files and linked to by the XHTML file.

Criticism of XML

Most of the criticism that I hear about XML falls into one of three categories.

HTML allows broken code

It used to be that when an HTML page was malformed, Web browsers wouldn't be able to render it. This was like any other file; when it's malformed, it doesn't make any sense to the renderer. However, back when competition between Web browser vendors was more fierce, Web browser venders started adding the ability to render malformed markup. In this way, Web developers that used those Web browsers wouldn't notice mistakes in their code, so those mistakes didn't get fixed. Other Web browsers that hadn't yet added the ability to render malformed documents weren't able to display these pages, and users blamed the Web browsers that conformed to the standard instead of those that had caused it: the Web browsers that *didn't* conform to the standard. The rendering of invalid HTML is a horrid artifact of a past war between software developers. It's not a good thing, but a blemish on the entire Web. If you try using the W3C validator on most Web pages, you'll find that even those developed by the most professional of companies often aren't even valid pages. Being able to see your page break and know to fix it is a *very good thing*, which is a big part of why we need XML.

HTML allows missing tags

Some people claim that omitting close tags is somehow cleaner because it's less verbose in some cases. HTML5 allows that practice in many cases. However, is that really cleaner? You're not telling the parser where your element stops. Instead, you're relying on the parser to end your element when another begins or when it finds itself unable to continue the element for some reason, such as when the container element ends. Omitting useful information isn't the way to write clean code. Leaving out closing tags is about as clean as leaving out closing parentheses.

Does this look very clean to you? (It's shorter, but that doesn't make it cleaner.

As a side note, XML also has a neat feature in which single tags look different than open tags. You might not find that useful if you know all of the tags available in your markup language, but often times, you know the subset of tags that you actually use or that you use most often. When looking at XML, you know when a tag you don't recognize is open or is a single tag with no close tag. You can even self-close empty tags. For example, I write <script src="/script/javascript.js" /> instead of <script src="/script/javascript.js"></script>. In HTML, there's no way to condense this, and you must always specify a close tag even when it makes no sense for the element to even be open. Otherwise, the entire rest of the page might be interpreted as malformed JavaScript instead of as HTML.

JSON (or something else) is better for storing data

XML isn't a data-storage format. It's a document markup format. It's Extensible Markup Language, after all, not Extensible Data-Storage Language. If you misuse a tool, sure, you'll get poor performance out of it. For example, if you store textual information as a PNG file and claim that that's what PNG files are for, it's going to make the PNG format look bad. PNG files are absolutely horrid for storing textual information. However, they excel at storing non-photographic graphic art. The same applies to XML. If you try to use XML as a data-storage format, you're going to get suboptimal results. If you're storing data, yes, JSON is the better format! However, it's not because JSON is actually a better format than XML at all. It's because JSON's strength is data storage while XML's strength is instead document markup.

XML for data storage

As I said, XML is a markup language, not a data-storage language. However, it can still be used effectively for data storage when used correctly. Much of the problem when developing an XML flavor for data storage that makes it inefficient is caused by people doing it wrong. Again, this isn't the fault of XML and doesn't mean that XML itself isn't good for what it's good at. Instead of having an element for each key/value pair, it's often more efficient to instead use attributes of a single element. According to Wikipedia, doing that results in file sizes that are just as small or only slightly larger than those achieved in JSON. Even when XML is the wrong tool for the job, it does pretty well when used with a little skill. Now that's impressive! Additionally, in XML, you can see what element is ending when it ends. In JSON, you can't do that. Instead, you have to count your layered braces to find the start of the nested element to know what element it is. Proper indention of course helps with this, but it helps in XML too.

Copyright © 2017 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.